Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrdan.
And today we're gonna be learning
how to use the periodic table.
And this is one of those most
vital skills that you could ever
have in any chemistry course.
So if you're someone who is new to
chemistry, I'm gonna go over the basics
on how to read an element that you find
on the periodic table and some of the
different applications that we can use by
learning how to use our periodic table.
This is introductory.
Every single class is gonna be
a different level, so I always
recommend knowing your fundamentals.
In this video, we'll go through how to
tell how number of protons, number of
electrons, how to calculate neutrons.
To apply it to the Bohr model,
and then we'll also learn how to
fill in common textbooks and exam
charts that you will find in this.
Go at it.
Let's learn how to read an
element from a periodic table.
The periodic table is something that
has all of our elements organized by
its property, and they're all identified
differently based on their number
of, based on their atomic number, the
number of protons, and all these little
subatomic particles that you were
learning about in your chemistry course.
What I have in front of us is sodium.
So, sodium is represented by the
element symbol Na, which is the
very first thing that we see here.
So every single element is represented
by a two letter or one letter
abbreviation, and that helps us be
able to identify it very quickly so
that way we don't have to spend a lot
of time trying to figure out exactly
what is this that we are looking at.
Above it, you can see that we have the
atomic number, which is how all our entire
Periodic table is situated and organized.
Now what is important about the atomic
number is that, well, whenever you
see an atomic number, this tells you
the number of protons as well as the
number of electrons for an atom, and
that is because every single atom
is inherently neutral, meaning it
does not have a charge naturally.
They are inherently neutral.
So now what else do we have here?
Well, we also have this
number on the bottom, which is
referring to the atomic mass.
Now the atomic mass is our third
number, which is also very useful.
And what that tells us is whenever we
add up all of our protons and all of
our neutrons, we will have our mass.
So this is protons plus neutrons
is equal to our mass above.
So, and that's something
that's a very common thing.
We commonly will round this number to
the nearest whole number, um, being that
it represents different versions of each
element known as isotopes, which we will
cover in future videos about isotopes.
So let's try to apply this and
try to organize it in a simple
model known as the Bohr model.
So let's look at this one
in the next example, right?
So with the Bohr model, the
entire idea with this is for
us to be able to organize.
All of our protons, electrons, and
neutrons in a very simple manner.
Now, when you are reading your periodic
table, you have your atomic number, which
tells you how many protons there are.
This is what identifies your element.
You cannot change the number of protons.
It is unique for your element.
So we had sodium above.
So we have all of our protons and
neutrons are found within the nucleus
now at an atomic number of 11.
That means that we have 11
protons inside of our center.
So our 11 e with a plus tells you protons.
Now, how do I figure out neutrons?
Well, you remember from
before the atomic mass, right?
So our atomic mass from right here
tells us, all right, that's 23, right?
We're gonna round that up.
Now 23 is equal to protons plus neutrons.
So let's do some simple math here.
23 minus 11.
How many do we have left?
So we have 12 neutrons is what is left.
Now notice if I add those two
together, that equals your atomic mass.
That's everything that's inside.
What about the electrons?
Nucleus is in that dense little core
right in the middle, but around it, our
electrons are moving as extremely fast.
As a blur around the nucleus
in an electron cloud.
Now, what early physicists believed
is that, okay, well let's try to
organize these things in orbits, which
are little circles around each orbit.
Now around the nucleus, the electrons
are found equidistant away from that
nucleus trying to rotate around.
Now this model is something that
is a beginning model, right?
Eventually we'll realize, oh, this
gets a little bit more complicated
when we learn the next steps
with electronic configuration.
But for now, it is a nice approach.
Now with this, it helps us to be
able to explain the periodic table.
So let's look at our periodic table
and try to understand how can we
try to situate electrons in it.
Now.
So here's a periodic table.
When we were looking at this, right?
We have sodium is all the
way over here on the left.
And the cool thing about this thing
is it not only tells you electrons,
protons, all this useful info, but
it also tells you how many levels
there are in this orbits, right?
Orbits are levels, or an easier
way of looking at this is
rows of your periodic table.
So if we have, how many rows do we have?
If you look here, right, we have
1, 2, 3, until you get to sodium.
So how do I figure out how many electrons
there are in each of my rows or orbits?
Well, it's like reading a book.
If you look at your first row,
how many elements are there?
Well, I can see that I have
hydrogen right up top left.
And then I also have helium over
on the top right over here, right?
So that's one, two.
So that means we have two
electrons in our first one.
So why don't we fill that in
so we go back up to our orbit.
What we're gonna do is we're gonna
put two dots for our electrons.
And it doesn't matter a hundred
percent where they're at, we're
just gonna put 'em in there, right?
So that's where it is.
Now, going back to our periodic
table again, how many do I have
in the second and third row?
Well count.
Count your columns now in that row.
So if I look at that second row,
well, all right, I see that I have
lithium beryllium, so that's  1, 2.
And we'll go across read from left
to left to right, like a book.
We see we have 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, and then eight.
There's the same number
below it so we can fit eight.
So we'll put eight dots until we run out.
Now we gotta make sure we don't go
over 11 electrons for this example.
So we have two in the first row, and
then we'll have eight in the next.
And we'll put in eight dots, right?
1, 2, 3, 4.
5, 6, 7, and then eight.
Now how many do I have left?
I've put a total of 10 in there so far.
We need one more, right?
11 protons equals 11 electrons.
So that last one is gonna go
in our final row because in our
final count we have 11 protons, 12
neutrons, and then 11 electrons.
And that is how we can show do it
for sodium with the Bohr model.
Let's go on to further topics of what
else we can get from our Periodic table.
Even though I said earlier, and it is
true, atoms are inherently neutral.
However, they have the tendency
to take or lose electrons that are
around them if they so remember,
protons have to always be the same.
We never lose a proton.
We only ever lose electrons.
They're really tiny.
They move really fast, sometimes easy to
misplace, sometimes easy to borrow them.
If you have a cat ion, meaning that
it has an extra or has one less
electron cat ions, cats are positive.
So if you remember, cat ion
means you have one less electron.
So let's write that down for ourselves.
Write one less electron.
One less electron.
Now if you have an ion or you thinking
an onion, which is a little bit
negative 'cause it makes you cry, right?
If you have an anion, that means
you have one more electron.
So keep in mind, you will also be
given ions, which are very important
to realize when it comes to charge.
Charge is gonna be something that's
a big part of trying to see how are
these different species bonding to
each other as we're going through
all these different examples.
So let's try and see how we can
organize these with the Bohr
model when we are altering our
charges onto our next example.
Okay.
In our next example, what we're
gonna be looking at is how else we
can try to organize elements and how
to read them when you come across
them, whether on a periodic table
or in different homework problems.
So one common way that you will see a lot
of these different elements represented is
in the following notation, where you have
an element symbol, like how we have the
one, uh, down here with chlorine, right?
We have our symbol in the middle.
That's generally written with
the letter X just to tell you,
okay, here's their symbol.
It's very common that this will
have a charge associated with it.
If it's neutral, it's gonna be a zero.
If it's positive, it'll be
like plus one, plus two, plus
three, plus four, and so on.
If it's negative, same idea,
negative one, negative two,
negative three, negative four.
In this case, we just have
negative or negative one.
This is telling you how many more or
how many less electrons do you have?
From before.
If you remember your atomic number,
it's very commonly written with the
letter Z to tell you, okay, atomic
number, how many protons or your
atomic mass, which is, how heavy is it?
Protons and neutrons are
heavier, therefore we add
those up to get our total.
Alright, let's try to
practice that and with ions.
So here's our example from earlier
on the left, we have sodium.
Now, if you remember,
let's practice that again.
How many protons do we have?
Well, that's going off our atomic number
or the number on the top left here.
So when we have that right, we
have 11 protons in our nucleus.
Now we're subtracting the mass
from the number of protons.
So when we subtract those two
numbers, 23 minus 11, that tells
you, alright, well we're gonna have.
Uh, 12 neutrons in my nucleus.
Now, what about the charge?
Well, it's positive, meaning that it
has a much more positive presence.
Protons are positive, electrons
are negative, meaning that I have
more protons than I have electrons.
In this case.
The way to think about
this is think of a balance.
One more positive.
That means my protons are a little
bit heavier than my electrons.
So if we have 11 protons, that must
mean we have 10 electrons that have
that positive charge in this molecule.
So we will fill those in.
And remember, we have two
electrons in the first level.
We have eight in the second.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Seven and then eight.
So that is a total of 10 electrons,
which is how many we have in a positive
sodium atom or ion, sorry, not atom.
Okay.
Now the next one, chlorine
chlorine's a little bit bigger.
One thing that you'll see is that it
has 17, uh, 17 as its atomic number.
Meaning how many protons is that?
Well, it's gonna have.
17 protons, right?
Those numbers are equal.
Next, when we are looking at
our neutrons and protons, right,
this is what makes up our mass.
We add those together.
So we do 35 minus 17.
You are gonna get how many
remaining neutrons are.
So we have 18 neutrons in our atom now 17.
So we, no, we normally have 17
electrons to balance out the 17 protons.
Being that this chlorine has
a negative one charge, that
means we have one more electron.
'cause we're more negative,
we're more like an anion or
more like an onion in this case.
So being that it's the case,
we will fill in our electrons.
We have two in the first
level, eight in the next 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and an eight.
And then we're gonna have another
eight in the next level as well.
And maybe we'll do these different
colors just to help show each level.
And then we'll do, let's do gold for
the last 1, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
And they don't have to
be in a specific spot.
We're just trying to show that
we have two electrons in that
first level, or N is equal to one.
And is equal to two as in
row, two is eight and is equal
to three, is another eight.
As I have written in the little chart
here, like how we looked in the periodic
table before, and that's how you fill
in a Bohr model for different ions.
Let's go into a very common exam problem
where we try to calculate protons,
neutrons, and electrons with something
you can find in most tests or homework.
It's very commonly given at
schools all across the country.
Let's go to it.
All right.
The very common problem that you
get all the time in text tests,
quizzes, homeworks, is a fill
on a table just like this one.
Now, the whole idea about this table is
that you are given piece of information
and you need to try to solve the
unknown pieces from what you are
given, so you gotta complete the table.
Now what thing you see is that,
alright, what do I give you?
Well, you have the symbol, you have the
atomic number, the mass number of protons,
the number of electrons, neutrons, charge.
That's everything that we got from before.
So if we are to fill this out, well,
let's see what context clues are.
If we know the number of protons
or the element symbol, then we
can figure out the rest of the
information really easily in this case.
For the first one, we have
the number of protons 16.
That's a fingerprint of a molecule, right?
That's exactly the number
of any of these species.
So atomic number is equal
to the number of protons.
So let's try to figure out what is,
so we're looking for number 16, and
when we look at the periodic table,
well real quick, we can see that,
oh, sulfur over here is number 16.
So, Now we're not gonna copy
down the mass from this.
We are using what is given.
Only the atomic number and symbol are
we gonna take from the periodic table.
So we will use our own information.
So we have sulfur is our
element, so let's fill that in.
So we have S and it has a symbol of 16.
Now I gave you the mass, which is 32
for this particular version of sulfur.
So how do you figure out neutrons?
Well, neutrons is our at atomic mass
is neutrons plus protons, right?
So being that we have our mass of 32,
we can do 32 minus 16 protons is gonna
be equal to 16 neutrons for our problem.
So we can fill in that
piece of information.
So 16 neutrons.
How many have now what about electrons?
Okay, well we have another little
formula here is that charge is
equal to protons plus electrons.
And then I give you a little key that
cat ions are positive and ions are
negative, meaning more electrons or less.
And one thing that we can see is,
okay, we had a charge of negative two.
So if we go back down, that means
that we're more like an anion, right?
We are more negative, so
we have more electrons.
Now we also see that protons.
Are equal to, or protons plus
electrons equals our charge.
So if we have a charge of negative
two and then we have 16 protons,
we want to know how many electrons.
Well, if we do minus 16 or minus two
minus 16, we'll get a negative 18,
which is 18 electrons if we do the
little algebra behind it, 18 electrons.
And that's how you fill these out.
So I bet you will have homework
problems like this in your class.
Most classes do, and it's a practice Do.
Can you fill it out and if you wanted
to put this in one step farther in the
atomic notation like we had earlier, we
could do that where, okay, well I have
sulfur as Adam 16 and it has a mass of 32.
With a negative two charge, you
could fill in all of the information
given to you and with that symbol,
which is really, really useful.
Alright, the next one,
copper Plus and 36 neutrons.
That's all we have, but we can use our
periodic table to figure out how many
protons and what the atomic number are.
Remember those are equal to each other.
So let's find copper on the periodic
table that has a metal that's gonna
be right here in the middle and
we can see it right here, right?
So copper, that is number 29.
And just from earlier
sulfur was over here.
Just the circle that.
So 29 is our number of protons and our
number, uh, and our atomic number as well.
So let's fill that in.
So 29, and then we also have 29 protons.
Now what can we do next?
Well, we have protons and we
also have the neutrons as well.
So we can add up those two things
together to get our mass number.
So 29 plus 36.
That's gonna be 55 for our mass.
So we have those.
We could fill in our little guy over
here, like how we did before 55 and 29.
Good practice to do.
I recommended it on all your homeworks.
Now what else do we need?
We need the number of
electrons and the charge.
Well, if you notice over here on the
problem, It had a little positive
charge written next to it, which
tells you, okay, well if I have
this positive here, that means that
there's one less electron, right?
This is a cat ion.
Cats are positive.
So if this is a cation, that
means we have one more proton.
So we have a total of 28 electrons
and a positive one charge.
And I can show you the math for that too.
So if it's positive one and we have 29
plus our electrons, we could see that.
All right, well if I subtract
those two numbers together, we
will get to negative 28, which
is electrons 'cause are negative.
Right?
And that's how you can
solve this type of problem.
Well, I hope that this video helped.
This goes through all the different
problems that you commonly see for just
the basics and the fundamentals of how
to count protons, electrons, and neutrons
when you are in your chemistry class.
I will try to leave it on that
screen here just so you have
all those little tips and notes.
But good luck to you and there
will be more videos to come.
And this is Dr.
Dan here.
Please feel free to hit that like
and subscribe button if this helped.
And I hope to see you in future videos.
Thank you, and I'll see you all later.
Bye.